<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Xavier's Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[I am a senior software engineer working mostly in Java. I live in Montreal. Everything I write in this blog do not engage the responsibility of anyone else.]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 01:28:49 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[From JBake to Hubpress]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Somedays ago I watched a 2015 Devoxx Fr Video about Asciidoc and Hubpress and  I chose to migrate my blog from JBake to Hubpress.</p>
</div>
<div class="videoblock">
<div class="content">
<iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kyGJEVEjfAs?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Already liked Asciidoc but I was not totally satisfied with JBake so I decided to give Hubpress a try. Will tell you about it after some posts.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/10/29/From-J-Bke-to-Hubpress.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/10/29/From-J-Bke-to-Hubpress.html</guid><category><![CDATA[HubPress]]></category><category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category><category><![CDATA[JBake]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lost your OSMC password ? Reset it]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>A few weeks ago, I decided to change the default osmc password to something more secure.
Of course I managed to forget this secured password.
Fortunately for me there is a way to reset it without damaging anything.</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Stop your raspberry</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Remove your sdcard and plug it in another computer</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>On the sdcard edit the file cmdline.txt</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Write init=/bin/bash at the end of the first line</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Save the file and plug back the sdcard in your raspberry</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Power the RB and Run passwd osmc</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Change your password</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Remove init=/bin/bash the same you used to write it in the cmdline.txt</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Et voilà</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Have fun.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/05/29/Lost-your-OSMC-password-Reset-it.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/05/29/Lost-your-OSMC-password-Reset-it.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Osmc]]></category><category><![CDATA[Password]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to change the mail subject in outlook 2016]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>For a while now I have been wondering how to best organise my mails.
Now I have found a tip very useful to me : rewrite the subject of your inbox mails.</p>
</div>
<div class="olist arabic">
<ol class="arabic">
<li>
<p>Open the mail</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click in subject</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Type the new subject</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Save the mail</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Et voilà</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/05/29/How-to-change-the-mail-subject-in-outlook-2016.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/05/29/How-to-change-the-mail-subject-in-outlook-2016.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Outlook]]></category><category><![CDATA[Subject]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Vaadin 8]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Last week, I had the chance to attend to the Vaadin talk by @marcushellberg (Marcus Hellberg) hosted by the Montreal Jug.
I have been so impressed that I am pretty sure I will write my next webapp with Vaadin.
I decided to give Vaadin a try and get back to Angular if I am not convinced.
My choice is mainly based on two facts :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>I am more productive in Java than in Angular</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Vaadin is a pretty mature</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Vaadin is Rich Internet Application framework first released in year 2002.
In 2007 the  the product license was changed to open source Apache License 2.0.
The version 8 of Vaadin just came out two month ago with many enhancements.
Such as :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Re-written data binding API utilizing modern Java features, such as type parameters and lambda expressions</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>CPU and memory improvements</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To help you see what Vaadin can help you do, you can watch this video : <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qUBt8k4pQgQ">Vaadin 8</a>.
This is mostly the same presentation I saw at Montreal Jug.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You can find the code of the demo on Github. Follow this <a href="https://github.com/vaadin-marcus/spring-boot-todo">link</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I was able to develop the note app in a bit more of time than Marcus but I did it in less than an hour.
From this starting point, I am learning through the Vaadin <a href="https://vaadin.com/docs/">documentation</a></p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/04/18/Vaadin-8.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/04/18/Vaadin-8.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Vaadin]]></category><category><![CDATA[Spring]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Se déconnecter des réseaux sociaux]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Il y a quelques semaines, suite à la visualisation d&#8217;une conférence <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3E7hkPZ-HTk">TED</a>, j&#8217;ai décidé de fortement limiter mon utilisation des réseaux sociaux.
Je voulais vérifier l&#8217;impact que les réseaux sociaux avaient sur ma vie.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>J&#8217;ai eu l&#8217;occasion de passer par 3 phases :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>la déconnexion</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>la reconstruction</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>l'évangélisation</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Tout d&#8217;abord, la déconnexion. Celle-ci m&#8217;est venue du constat que la majeure partie, si ce n&#8217;est la totalité de mon temps passé sur les réseaux sociaux ne m&#8217;apportait absolument rien. Ça avait même, de temps en temps, un impact négatif sur ma joie de vivre.
Pour faciliter ma déconnexion, j&#8217;ai choisi de rendre complexe ma connexion aux réseaux sociaux par 3 moyens :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>suppression des applications mobiles</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>suppression de l&#8217;enregistrement du mot de passe</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>désactivation des notifications de mes différents réseaux sociaux</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Les applications mobiles donnent un accès facile aux réseaux sociaux. Et nous avons tendance à les utiliser dès que l&#8217;ennui survient ou lorsque nous attendons.
Mon utilisation de ces applications était ponctuelle mais très régulière et donc très consommatrice en temps.
Ça ne semble pas grand chose et pourtant, le temps de saisie d&#8217;un mot de passe me permet de me poser la question suivante :</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Quelle est la raison qui me pousse à me connecter ? et donc de prendre conscience que c&#8217;est inutile.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Ma déconnexion est totale sur Facebook si bien que certains amis m&#8217;ont contacté pour savoir si j&#8217;allais bien.
Idem sur LinkedIn.
J&#8217;utilise Twitter de manière quotidienne de manière beaucoup moins régulière. Genre une à deux fois par jour.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Dans un deuxième temps, il m&#8217;a fallu me reconstruire. Le mot paraît fort mais saviez-vous que les réseaux sociaux
embauchent des gens dont le métier est d&#8217;attirer votre attention pour que vous restiez sur leur réseau.
Ils utilisent certaines techniques très utilisées à Las Vegas. Si vous voyez ce que je veux dire&#8230;&#8203;
J&#8217;ai donc pris de nouvelles habitudes afin de remplacer le temps perdu sur les réseaux sociaux par du temps utile.
Voici une petite liste de ce que je fais maintenant que j&#8217;ai du temps :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>lire des livres</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>écrire (ce post notamment)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>réfléchir sur les différentes choses que je souhaite faire</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Ces habitudes me rendent plus heureux et me permettent d'évoluer à contrario du temps que je perdais sur les réseaux sociaux. Au fur et à mesure, je me rends compte que le temps qui me manquait avant peut se trouver en supprimant le superflu.
Je finis donc par me dire qu&#8217;en plus des réseaux sociaux, je peux supprimer d&#8217;autres activités comme certaines séries télé ou des activités en ligne.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Au moment d'écrire ce post, je suis au stade de l'évangélisation. Je dis à mon entourage de tester la déconnexion pour voir ce que ça peut leur apporter. Après à chacun de déterminer où se trouve leur intérêt.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Personnellement, après un mois le bilan est assez positif puisque j&#8217;ai trouvé le temps :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>de me former à certains outils</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>de lire un livre par semaine minimum</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>de lancer et écrire ce blog</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>de passer du temps de qualité avec mes proches</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>de faire un peu de sport</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Mais pour moi, le plus gros gain se trouve au niveau du focus dans ce que je fais et donc de mon efficacité.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Et vous c&#8217;est pour quand ?</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/04/11/Se-deconnecter-des-reseaux-sociaux.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/04/11/Se-deconnecter-des-reseaux-sociaux.html</guid><category><![CDATA[SocialNetworks]]></category><category><![CDATA[Life]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why I use asciidoc to take my notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>For some time now I have used asciidoc to write all my notes.
I even use asciidoc to write this blog.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My main use case was that I wanted to be able to send a proper report of what I was doing especially when investing a problem.
I took this habit while working with an architect who sent a note to the project manager at the end of each day when working on a problem.
This note contained all his paths of research.
Such note was really helpful when you had to work on the problem after him.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The advantages I find in using asciidoc are :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Clear syntax (<a href="http://asciidoctor.org/docs/asciidoc-syntax-quick-reference/">quick syntax</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Can generate proper output in many formats</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Can easily be reused in a project documentation</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Only need a simple text editor</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I had to find some disadvantages :</p>
</div>
<div class="ulist">
<ul>
<li>
<p>Need to have some tools installed to use all the features</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Have to learn the syntax to properly modify a note</p>
</li>
</ul>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>For me no better argument than an example to really show you why I use asciidoc :</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><a href="https://github.com/mikrethor/blog/tree/master/src/main/asciidoc/asciidoc-note-example.ad">source</a> &#8594; <a href="https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/blog/2017/asciidoc-note-example.pdf">output</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To properly and easily access my notes I push them in a git repository but I have heard about using asciidoc with Evenote (<a href="https://emmanuelbernard.com/blog/2017/03/28/evernote-and-vim/">asciidoc vim Evernote</a>).</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/03/29/Why-I-use-asciidoc-to-take-my-notes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2017/03/29/Why-I-use-asciidoc-to-take-my-notes.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Notes]]></category><category><![CDATA[Asciidoc]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[[MAVEN] settings en ligne de commande]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Indiquer un settings.xml pour maven en ligne de commande
Il est possible de surcharger les settings.xml de base pour maven.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>mvn install --settings c:\user\settings.xml
    --global-settings c:\global\settings.xml</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2011/11/14/MAVEN-settings-en-ligne-de-commande.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mikrethor.github.io/blog/2011/11/14/MAVEN-settings-en-ligne-de-commande.html</guid><category><![CDATA[Maven]]></category><category><![CDATA[Settings]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[mikrethor]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>